Okay, today's דף Daf is ל"ד, Lamed Dalet, גיטין ל"ד, Gittin Lamed
Dalet, we pick up six lines from the top and where the
larger context is the משנה's Mishna discussion that a husband who sent
a גט Get to his wife can be מבטל Mevatel it as
long as the גט Get has not yet reached her and in
the past they used to even be able to make a בית
דין Beis Din and be מבטל Mevatel it without her being aware
of it and רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel put an end to that
practice because of תיקון עולם. Tikkun Olam. Okay so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this, six lines from the top ל"ד עמוד א':
Lamed Dalet Amud Aleph: גידל בר רעילאי שדרו ליה גיטא לדביתהו. Gidud
bar I'lai shadru lei gita l'devitehu. So גידל בר רעילאי, Gidud bar
I'lai,
some man, sent a גט Get to his wife. אזל שליחא אשכחה
דהוה יתבה
ונוולה. Azal shlicha ashkacha d'hava yatva v'navla. So the שליח Shliach came,
the messenger came, you know the agent, and saw that she was
sitting and she was knitting. אמר לה היי גיטיך. Amar lah hai
gitayich. So he said here's your גט. Get. אמרה ליה זיל השתא
מחר אתית. Amra lei zil hashta machar atit. She said, you know,
I'm not interested come tomorrow, it's like he's trying to serve, you
know, you've been served, but he was at least cordial enough and
she said come back tomorrow and he decided to come back tomorrow
even though he could have given it to her, a man can
divorce his wife against her will, but anyway that's what happened. Okay
so אזל לגביה, Azal legabeih, so he went back to גידל בר
רעילאי Gidud bar I'lai who sent him, ואמר ליה, V'amar lei, and
he told him what happened, you know, your wife told me to
come back tomorrow. פתח ואמר ברוך הטוב והמטיב. Patach v'amar Baruch Hatov
Vehametiv.
So גידל בר רעילאי, Gidud bar I'lai, you know, answered back and
said like oh ברוך השם, Baruch Hashem, ברוך הטוב והמטיב. Baruch Hatov
Vehametiv. Thank God that you didn't actually deliver it. It was clear
that he had remorse and he did not want to have divorced
his wife.
Okay now אביי אמר ברוך הטוב והמטיב ולא בטיל גיטא. Abaye amar
Baruch Hatov Vehametiv v'lo batil gita. So he said ברוך הטוב והמטיב
Baruch Hatov Vehametiv but he was not מבטל Mevatel the גט Get
and if the שליח Shliach was to decide to continue to deliver
the גט, Get, it would still be good. So, you know, the
language of אביי Abaye is לא בטיל גיטא lo batil gita and
that's the language of the משנה, Mishna, you know, to be מבטל
Mevatel the
גט. Get. רש"י Rashi here speaks about being מבטל Mevatel the
שליחות. Shlichut. In order to say that it would still be good
you have to say both are true, that even though he made
it clear that he did not want her to be divorced, א',
Aleph, it does not constitute a ביטול Bitul of the גט. Get.
Okay that's one thing, you know,
because we don't even exactly understand what that means, a ביטול Bitul
of the גט. Get. How does that work? You know, the classic
understanding is there's some type of לשמה Lishmah that the husband puts
into the גט Get and it's connected to him and therefore he
could be מבטל Mevatel it, but okay maybe therefore you need a
particular speech act to be מבטל Mevatel the power of the גט
Get to make the גט Get no longer
an effective document. But the שליחות, Shlichut, the agency, right, you would
think that logically if it's clear that he no longer wants to
divorce his wife that that maybe, you know, the שליחות Shlichut would
end. But אביי's Abaye point is no, we know what his intent
is but until he actually revokes the agency and until he actually
is מבטל Mevatel the גט, Get, all of that remains in place.
Okay ברוך הטוב והמטיב ולא בטיל גיטא. Baruch Hatov Vehametiv v'lo batil
gita. רבא אמר ברוך הטוב והמטיב ובטיל גיטא. Rava amar Baruch Hatov
Vehametiv u'batil gita. No, the גט Get is בטל Batil and again
the simple language here is that the גט Get is בטל Batil
but רש"י Rashi more emphasizes that the שליחות Shlichut is בטל, Batil,
but if he were to deliver the גט Get the נפקא מינה
Nafka Mina would be that if he then were to reappoint the
שליח, Shliach, if you think that the גט Get is בטל Batil
then you would have to actually use a new גט. Get. But
anyway, okay, so רבא Rava says that one way or another, once
we know his intent, it's, you know, minimally the שליחות Shlichut is
בטל. Batil. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, ברוך
הטוב והמטיב ובטיל גיטא. Baruch Hatov Vehametiv u'batil gita. במאי קמיפלגי? Bemai
kamiflagi? What's the debate? בגילוי דעתא בגיטא קמיפלגי, Begilui da'ata begita kamiflagi,
whether when one reveals their intent by a גט Get is that
enough to negate the שליחות Shlichut or to be מבטל Mevatel the
גט, Get, right? It's not a question of what his דעת Da'as
is, it's very clear here what his דעת Da'as is, but he
did not do a specific act of being מבטל Mevatel the גט
Get or of negating the שליחות. Shlichut. בגיטא
לאו מילתא היא. Begita lav milta hi. רבא, Rava, so אביי סבר
גילוי דעתא בגיטא לאו מילתא היא, Abaye savar gilui da'ata begita lav
milta hi, that has no value, that the fact that we know
his desire, you know, you have to actually revoke it. Makes a
lot of sense from a legal standpoint. ורבא סבר גילוי דעתא בגיטא
מילתא היא. V'Rava savar gilui da'ata begita milta hi. No, that's enough,
once it's no longer being given with his wishes the שליח Shliach
can no longer be said to be acting on his behalf.
Okay, מילתא היא. Milta hi. אמר רבא מנא אמינא לה, Amar Rava
mana amina lah, how do I, where do I get this idea
that גילוי דעת Gilui Da'as is enough?
דרב ששת אשכחינהו להנהו סהדי, D'Rav Sheshet ashkachinhu l'hanei sahadi, רב ששת
Rav Sheshet sort of compelled a man to divorce his wife against
his will, and this is obviously something that sometimes we wish we
could do today, but the גמרא Gemara allows for cases where if
it's operating through the בית דין, Beis Din, a Jewish בית דין,
Beis Din, and there's justifiable reasons, you know, then they can the
Jewish בית דין Beis Din can force a person to divorce his
wife and force him to say I want to, you know, by
twisting his arm behind his back. So that was the case. So
רב ששת Rav Sheshet forced a man to divorce his wife against
his will, so he was resistant, but in the end he said
I want to because of the pressure of בית דין. Beis Din.
ואמר להו לסהדי הכי אמר לכו רב ששת לבטולי גיטא. V'amar lehu
l'sahadi hachi amar lacho Rav Sheshet l'vatulei gita. And then, you know,
after he sort of appointed the witnesses to go ahead and to,
you know, write the גט Get and to deliver the גט, Get,
he said, oh, רב ששת Rav Sheshet actually said that the גט
Get is בטל. Batel.
Okay so that's what he said to them. ואשכחיה רב ששת לגיטא
אחרינא V'ashkachei Rav Sheshet l'gita achrina
and now רב ששת Rav Sheshet found another גט. Get. So clearly
like he never was formally מבטל mevatel the שליחות shlichus or never
did a ביטול bitul of the גט, get, but somehow by making
clear that he was not really interested in the גט, get, maybe
by making up this story about רב ששת, Rav Sheshet, but he
made it clear that he wasn't interested, that was considered to be
enough of a problem that it nullified the שליחות shlichus or nullified
the גט. get. So that's my evidence that גילוי דעת gilluy da'as
is enough. אביי, Abaye, what would אביי Abaye respond back? אביי Abaye
would say אטו רב ששת מבטל גיטא דאינשי הוה? Atu Rav Sheshet
mevatel gitta de'inshei havae? The whole story doesn't make sense, right? רב
ששת Rav Sheshet said that the גט get is בטל. batel. I
mean, you know, like רב ששת Rav Sheshet is not in a
position to be מבטל mevatel other people's גט. get. Now of course
for somebody who's, you know, who's an עם הארץ, am ha'aretz, an
ordinary person doesn't necessarily understand that, and if the court is forcing
him to write it, maybe he thinks that the court has an
ability to nullify. But anyway, but אביי Abaye thinks that the whole
story doesn't make sense, okay? איהו בטליה. Ihu batlei. So actually what
happened was was that he actually did do an act of ביטול.
bitul. והאי דקאמר להו הכי משום דפנויי. Ve'hai d'ka'amar lehu hachi mishum
d'pinuyei.
And the reason he said it to them this way, משום דפנויי,
mishum d'pinuyei, because of the lashes. Meaning that he actually was מבטל
mevatel it after he told the witnesses to write it, then he
said, okay, I'm מבטל mevatel it, and then the court officers were
lashing him and beating him up and saying you're not allowed to
do that, and he was giving an excuse and he said no,
no, רב ששת Rav Sheshet told me that I could, רב ששת,
Rav Sheshet, you know, said that I should be מבטל mevatel the
גט. get. So basically אביי Abaye has a completely different story about
this than רבא. Rava. רבא's Rava story is is that he said
something which is false but it made it clear he wanted to
be מבטל mevatel the גט, get, and אביי's Abaye story is no,
he actually was actively מבטל mevatel the גט, get, and that's why
we required another גט, get, and sort of the name of רב
ששת Rav Sheshet was to get the people to stop beating him
up even though it was a lie. Okay, ואמר אביי, Ve'amar Abaye,
now אביי Abaye says that's רבא's Rava proof. ואמר אביי מנא אמינא
לה. Ve'amar Abaye mana amina lah. Where do I get this idea?
דרב יהודה אשכחיה לחתניה דרב
ירמיה ביראה. DeRav Yehuda ashkechei l'chatneih deRav Yirmiyah Birah. Because
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda again, forced a גט get to be written
for his, for the son-in-law of רב ירמיה ביראה. Rav Yirmiyah Birah.
Okay, so רב ירמיה ביראה's Rav Yirmiyah Birah son-in-law, he forced him
to give a גט get to רב ירמיה's Rav Yirmiyah daughter. ובטליה.
U'batlei. Okay, and then this person that was being forced to and
said, okay, fine, I want to, and then assigned witnesses to write
the גט, get, as soon as they stopped beating him up, then
he was מבטל mevatel the גט. get. Okay, תנא אשקליה ובטליה. Tana
ashkaleih u'batlei. So then he did it again. He forced him again
to say yes, I want to, and command the witnesses or whatever,
the סופר sofer to write the גט. get. And then again, you
know, he was מבטל mevatel it. הדר תנא ואשקליה על כרחיה. Hadar
tana v'ashkaleih al korcheih.
So once again he sort of, he got him to do it
and forced him to do it. Here it says explicitly he forced
him. ואמר להו לסהדי אותיבו כרי באוזנייכו. Ve'amar lehu l'sahadei otivu karrei
b'oznaichu.
And he said to the witnesses, put a gourd in your ear,
you know, I can't hear you because I've got a carrot in
my ear, so put a gourd in your ear, אותיבו כרי באוזנייכו,
otivu karrei b'oznaichu, וכתובו ליה, vechitivu leih,
and go ahead and write the
גט. get. Okay, so basically make sure you can't hear him telling
you that he is מבטל mevatel the גט get or being מבטל
mevatel you, you know, your ציווי tzivui for you to write the
גט get on his behalf. ואי סלקא דעתך גילוי דעת
בגיטא מילתא היא.
Ve'i salka
dachtech gilluy da'as begitta miltha hi. Now,
that makes sense if you need a formal retraction and the formal
retraction has to be directly given to the people who were commanded
to go ahead and write the גט get or deliver the גט.
get. So okay, so then makes sense, just, you know, make sure
you're not in earshot, plug up your ears. מילתא היא. Miltha hi.
Right, but ואי סלקא דעתך גילוי דעת בגיטא מילתא היא, ve'i salka
dachtech gilluy da'as begitta miltha hi,
but if you think that revealing your intent suffices and you don't
need a formal retraction, והא חזו ליה דקא רהי בתרייהו, ve'ha chazu
leih d'ka rahi batraihu, they see that he's running and trying to
tell them, you know, to call on them and retract it and
being מבטל mevatel it. Meaning he's making it very clear with all
of his actions even if they can't hear a formal withdrawal. So
this story only makes sense if you need a formal act of
withdrawal that you can prevent yourself from hearing that, but it doesn't
make sense if demonstrated desire to be מבטל mevatel suffices. So how
is רבא Rava going to answer this? ורבא האי דקא רהי בתרייהו
דאמר להו אשור הבו לה. VeRava hai d'ka rahi batraihu d'amar lehu
ashur havu lah. So רבא Rava would say no, go give it
to her quickly. So רבא Rava would say no, once you're stuffing
up your ears then you can allow yourself to reinterpret why is
he running after them? Oh, he's running after because he says just
give it to her already, give it to her already. So רבא
Rava would say yes, you need there to be גילוי דעת, gilluy
da'as, but maybe we can sometimes be creative based on the circumstances
in terms of whether we're determining whether or not גילוי דעת gilluy
da'as has been demonstrated. Okay, so רבא Rava has brought his proof
about from the story that it sounded like there was גילוי דעת
gilluy da'as and that was enough to nullify the process, and אביי
Abaye responded and said that that actually was an actual act of
ביטול. bitul. Then אביי Abaye gives his proof that it's enough to
plug up your ears, so clearly גילוי דעת gilluy da'as doesn't suffice.
And רבא's Rava response is essentially that we can, you know, maybe
under certain circumstances we can be creative based on the circumstances in
terms of whether we're determining whether or not גילוי דעת gilluy da'as
has been demonstrated. we can be creative, you know, and decide whether
or not we have actually seen sufficient גילוי דעת. gilu daas. Okay.
כי היכי דמשיצי צערא דהוא גברא ki heichi demishatzei tzara dehu gavra
go give it to her quickly that I should finally be done
with all of this pain and anguish that this whole process is
causing me. Okay and that's how we're going to interpret his running
after. Okay. ואמר אביי V'amar Abaye so we're not so we have
proofs in both ways that they've been managed to be disputed. ואמר
אביי מנא אמינא לה V'amar Abaye mena amina lah where do so
אביי Abaye is going to try again. Where do I get my
position that גילוי דעת gilu daas does not suffice you to do
a formal withdrawal? דהוא דאמר להו אי לא אתינא עד תלתין יומי
ליהוי גיטא Dehu de'amar lehu ee lo ateina ad tlatin yomei leihavei
gitta
a man gave a Get to his wife on a condition and
says, if I don't return within thirty days maybe he was afraid,
you know, that he would be lost, you know, that tragedy would
happen and his wife wouldn't know about it and she would be
an עגונה aguna there wouldn't be evidence. So he said if I
don't return or maybe it was just a normal תנאי, tnai, you
know, for whatever reason. Anyway he said, if I don't return within
thirty days, then it will be a Get. Okay. אתא ופסקיה מברא
ata upaskei mavra so he then he actually was on coming back
and he was ready to return to the city.
He was about to return to the city but there
was the ferry was on the other side of the river. So
basically he wanted to cross, you know, but he couldn't get over
within the thirty day limit. By the time the ferry would have
gotten there it would have been too late, but he was within
earshot, okay and what did he do? And he said חזו דאתאי
חזו
דאתאי chazu de'asai chazu de'asai
look look, I've arrived, I've come back, I've come back. So clearly
he didn't want he wanted it to be that the Get would
be בטל, battel, that the Get would not take effect. ואמר שמואל
v'amar Shmuel and שמואל Shmuel says, לאו שמיה מתיא. lav shemei matya.
Okay,
it's very nice he says I'm coming back, I'm coming back, I
want to come back. He didn't come back. Okay, and the condition
therefore was met that he didn't come back. ורבא v'Rava
so therefore, so what does אביי Abaye try to prove from that?
So אביי Abaye is trying to prove: you see that he has
intent, he doesn't want the Get to take effect, and nevertheless, tough
luck, the Get takes effect. Okay, so that's pretty clear, meaning: forget
the תנאי tnai is what אביי Abaye is saying. You know, the
תנאי tnai was satisfied. Okay fine, so he didn't return. But at
the same time he makes it clear that he doesn't want the
Get to take effect. Shouldn't that constitute a ביטול bittul of the
Get according to you, רבא? Rava? Why does it not constitute a
ביטול bittul of the Get for you, רבא, Rava, that גילוי דעת
gilu daas is enough? So let's see what רבא's Rava response is.
ורבא v'Rava and רבא Rava would say
back: אטו התם לביטולי גיטא בעי? atu hasam levitulei gitta baei? What,
is he trying to be מבטל mevattel the Get over there?
התם לקיומי תנאיה קא בעי hasam lekiyumei tnaia ka baei he's trying
to say I fulfilled my condition, I've returned. He's exactly the opposite
he didn't fulfill the condition. But okay, anyway, but he says basically
I've returned and he didn't return. He's focusing on trying to argue
that the condition of the Get has, you know, has been satisfied
or the non-effectiveness of the Get, the condition that it won't be
effective if I return, and that's not actually the case. Now that
seems a little bit non-responsive. It is true that that is what
he is arguing, but at the same point, it's also true that
he doesn't want the Get to take effect. But here, you know,
so why isn't גילוי דעת gilu daas enough? So here though, the
answer could be because what should the גילוי דעת gilu daas do?
Should the גילוי דעת gilu daas nullify the שליחות? shlichus? There is
no שליחות. shlichus. He gave the Get thirty days ago. He just
made a condition. Okay,
so the only thing the גילוי דעת gilu daas could do this
gets back to the question of whether we're trying to negate שליחות
shlichus or actually do ביטול bittul of the Get. So the גילוי
דעת gilu daas of ביטול bittul of a Get here is the
question. Whenever רבא Rava says that that suffices, does רבא Rava mean
that it suffices to know he doesn't want to divorce his wife
and that effects a ביטול bittul of the Get? That actually would
be a little bit surprising, right? Because the Get maybe he wants
to keep it in his, you know, in his dresser, you know,
in his desk, and pull it out at a later time if
he wants to use it. So גילוי דעת gilu daas might not
be enough that he knows he doesn't want to divorce his wife,
although that was the initial case. But גילוי דעת gilu daas to
do ביטול bittul of a Get might be that, you know, it's
clear that he wants to be מבטל mevattel the Get, he just
didn't say it. All right, so that's רבא's Rava response here. רבא's
Rava response is: Look, he's focused on the תנאי. tnai. Is it
clear that he doesn't want to divorce his wife? Yes, maybe it
is clear he doesn't want to divorce his wife, but that is
not enough to effect, even if I would go by גילוי דעת,
gilu daas, there's no גילוי דעת gilu daas of being מבטל mevattel
the Get. And there's also no שליחות shlichus to nullify here, so
tough luck, the Get takes effect. Okay. ורבא
אטו התם לביטולי גיטא בעי v'Rava atu hasam levitulei gitta baei he's
not trying to be מבטל mevattel the Get, meaning and his גילוי
דעת gilu daas is not about the status of the Get. התם
לקיומי תנאיה קא בעי hasam lekiyumei tnaia ka baei his focus is
on I satisfied my condition, the condition for the Get to not
take effect. והא לא אקיים תנאיה veha lo itkaiyam tnaia and that
did not and that he would like to think that he satisfied
it, but it was not because he did not get to the
city in time. Okay. ההוא דאמר להו Hahu de'amar lehu now another
case. A man said to ההוא דאמר להו אי לא נסיבנא עד
תלתין יומי hahu de'amar lehu ee lo nasivna ad tlatin yomei ליהוי
גיטא. lehava gitta. Okay, so he basically gave a גט get to
his wife and he said, you know, if because there was
קידושין kiddushin and his wife was pushing him to turn the קידושין
kiddushin into actually נישואין nissuin or to let her go and take
other offers. So he gave her a גט get and he said
if we don't do actually נישואין, nissuin, you know, the חופה chuppah
and actually start living together within thirty days, then this גט get
will take effect. Okay, so he gave her the גט get on
the condition that they do not get married within thirty days, meaning
נישואין, nissuin, there's already
קידושין. kiddushin. כי מטא תלתין יומין, ki mata t’lasin yomin, when thirty
days came about and he wasn't yet ready to have the חופה,
chuppah, but he says, look, look, I'm trying, I'm trying to put
together, you know, a down payment for the rent, I'm working on
it, I'm working on it, and so on. Okay, so is that
enough to be מבטל mevattel the גט? get? It's similar to the
previous discussion although here it seems even weaker. למאי ניחוש לה? l’mai
neichush lah? What should be the concern? אי משום אונס אין אונס
בגיטין. ei mishum ones ein ones b’gittin. If the point is like
I'm trying to satisfy the condition but it's out of my hands,
well the הלכה halacha there is that that claim of אונס, ones,
it’s out of my hands, does not work by a תנאי tenai
by a גט. get. Okay, that's a whole other סוגיא sugya somewhere
else, but that's the basic point, it does not work by a
תנאי tenai by a גט. get. So therefore,
the
condition is, at the end of the day he didn't satisfy the
condition even though it was under his hands and the גט get
takes effect. אי משום גילוי דעת בגיטו, ei mishum gilluy da’at b’gitto,
now how about the issue about גילוי דעת? gilluy da’at? פלוגתא דאביי
ורבא. plugta d’Abaye v’Rava. Okay, well אין הכי נמי, ein hachi nami,
that would be dependent on the debate of אביי Abaye and רבא.
Rava.
So the גט get certainly in terms of the condition, the condition
wasn't met, so therefore the גט get should take effect. Is his
גילוי דעת gilluy da’at enough to prevent it? That's the debate of
אביי Abaye and רבא. Rava. Now actually that doesn't seem to make
much sense because it seems to be very similar to the previous
case and תוספות Tosafot sort of says that, that you know based
on the הוה אמינא hava amina before it's the debate of אביי
Abaye and רבא, Rava, but actually the answer here could be that
even according to רבא, Rava, תפלק, t’flak, we know that you don't
want to divorce your wife but you are not but there's no
גילוי דעת gilluy da’at about actually being מבטל mevattel the גט get
and there's also no שליחות shlichus to be מבטל mevattel here. Okay,
ההוא דאמר להו hahu d'amar lehu אי לא נסיבנא לראש ירחא, ei
lo nasivna l’reish yarcha, another case, a man said to the witnesses
if I do not marry, again there was קידושין kiddushin so a
גט get is meaningful but there was no yet נישואין, nissuin, and
if we don't do the נישואין nissuin by ראש חודש אדר Rosh
Chodesh Adar ליהוי גיטא, lehava gitta,
let it be a גט. get. כי מטא ראש ירחא דאדר ki
mata reish yarcha d’Adar אמר להו amar lehu אדר ראש ירחא דניסן
אמרי. Adar reish yarcha d’Nissan amri. No, no, no, I didn't say
אדר, Adar, I said ניסן. Nissan. Now obviously the witnesses remembered that
he said אדר, Adar, you know, clearly he's lying or he's misremembering,
but either way it's clear that he doesn't want the גט get
to take effect. So אמר למאי ניחוש לה, amar l’mai neichush lah,
so what should we be concerned about here in terms of the
effectiveness of the גט? get? אי משום אונס אין אונס בגיטין. ei
mishum ones ein ones b’gittin. If we should say, well he's trying
and therefore maybe that should be considered like he satisfied the condition?
No, that's not true. You know, trying is not good enough and
even if it's out of your hands the condition wasn't met and
since the condition wasn't met, the גט get takes effect. He didn't
marry her by ראש חודש אדר, Rosh Chodesh Adar, the גט get
takes effect. אי משום גילוי דעתא, ei mishum gilluy da’ata, now how
about the fact that it's clear he doesn't want to divorce his
wife? פלוגתא דאביי ורבא. plugta d’Abaye v’Rava. Okay, that's a debate of
אביי Abaye and רבא Rava and again, at one hand it's the
debate of אביי Abaye and רבא Rava that רבא Rava might say
that גילוי דעת, gilluy da’at, you know, suffices to do a ביטול,
bitul, but on the other hand as רבא Rava said before as
we sort of, you know, it could be that even this גילוי
דעת gilluy da’at is not enough even according to רבא Rava because
it's a גילוי דעת gilluy da’at that he doesn't want the גט
get to take effect, but it's not a גילוי דעת gilluy da’at
of a ביטול. bitul. There's no שליחות shlichus to be מבטל mevattel
and there's no גילוי דעת gilluy da’at about being מבטל mevattel the
actual object of the גט get itself. Okay, והלכתא, v’hilcheta,
now
after all this discussion we're going to go back and reflect on
what the הלכה halacha is about also some stuff we did the
other day. והלכתא כנחמן, v’hilcheta k’Nachman, the הלכה halacha is like נחמן,
Nachman, okay, about the discussion we had the other day about being
מבטל mevattel in terms of
in front of two or in front of three. והלכתא כנחמן, v’hilcheta
k’Nachman, we also rule like the other רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, okay,
that he ruled like רבי Rebbi in both of the debates in
terms of whether בדיעבד b’di’avad the ביטול bitul would work if you
violated the תקנה. takkana. והלכתא כנחמני, v’hilcheta k’Nachmani, and we also rule
like נחמני. Nachmani. נחמני Nachmani is a name for אביי Abaye and
we rule like אביי Abaye that גילוי דעת בגיטא gilluy da’at b’gitta
is not sufficient and actually if you want to be מבטל mevattel
a גט get you have to do an active speech act of
ביטול bitul the גט get and presumably also if you want to
be מבטל mevattel the שליחות, shlichus, right, demonstrating
your lack of desire does not actually revoke the שליחות. shlichus. This
is one of the times where we rule like אביי Abaye against
רבא, Rava, it's יע"ל קג"ם ya’al kagam is the famous mnemonic and
this is the גמל gimel of יע"ל קג"ם, ya’al kagam, גילוי דעת
בגיטא. gilluy da’at b’gitta. Now why was אביי Abaye called נחמני? Nachmani?
So to take a look at רש"י, Rashi, he says second line
from the top נראה בעיני דעל שם שרבה בר נחמני גידל אביי
בביתו ולמדו תורה. nir b’einai d’al shem sheRabbah bar Nachmani gidel Abaye
b’veito v’limdo Torah. Okay, that's because he was actually raised אביי Abaye
was an orphan. Actually some people say
that the actual name אביי Abaye in the name אביי Abaye actually
you know there is also a hint to the idea that he
was an orphan, it's a ראשי תיבות, rashei teivos, the מהרש"א Maharsha
says the idea of אשר בך ירוחם יתום. asher b’cha yerucham yasom.
יתום, yasom, you know that the orphan through God, you know, the
orphan will be consoled. So, so anyway, there's a question of exactly
what his original name is according to רש"י, Rashi, his real his
given name was אביי Abaye but he was called נחמני Nachmani because
he was raised by רבה בר נחמני Rabbah bar Nachmani which which
is just סתם רבה. stam Rabbah. Others, you know, sort of flip
it and actually say that נחמני Nachmani his actual name was נחמני
Nachmani but because of it sounded too much like רבה בר נחמני
Rabbah bar Nachmani or רבה בר נחמני's Rabbah bar Nachmani's father, you
know, who was his that, you know, who raised him, they gave
him this name of אביי. Abaye. And again the word of אביי
Abaye the מהרש"א Maharsha explains based on this ראשי תיבות rashei teivos
very beautiful אשר בך ירוחם יתום. Asher b'cha yerucham yasom. Okay, anyway,
so we rule like אביי ורבא Abaye v'Rava גם gam גילוי דעת
gilluy da'as בגט b'get is not sufficient. Next משנה. Mishnah. And within
this context of listing things of תיקון עולם tikkun olam and still
within the world of גיטין. Gittin. בראשונה היה משנה שמו ושמה שם
עירו ושם עירה. Berishona haya mishane shemo v'shma shem iro v'shem ira.
Originally they would change his name or her name, the name of
the city of his city or her city. Now that's a little
bit bizarre, right? I mean why would they allow to use a
wrong name, to change the name? So as we'll sort of see
it really doesn't mean change the name but it means using the
name that was a secondary name or not making it clear what,
you know, if there were multiple names, not citing all of the
names, or using a name that was the name recognized in one
place but not in the other place. So there was lack of
full clarity in terms of the names that were being used. התקין
רבן גמליאל הזקן שיהא כותב איש פלוני וכל שום שיש לו אשה
פלונית וכל שום שיש לה מפני תיקון עולם. Hitkin Rabban Gamliel Hazaken
sheyehei kosev ish ploni v'chol shum sheyesh lo isha plonis v'chol shum
sheyesh la mipnei tikkun olam. רבן גמליאל הזקן Rabban Gamliel Hazaken established
that they should write this man and any name that he has
and this woman and any name that she has because of תיקון
עולם. tikkun olam. Now of course there's a very fascinating debate in
the ראשונים Rishonim and a very important הלכה halachic debate which is
how do you read those words כל שום שיש לה? kol shum
sheyesh la? Do you read that in quote marks or in like
parentheses, fill in the name here? So would you actually write שרה
Sarah and every other, you know, and all other names by which
she might be known, is that what he established? Or the more
it's more seemingly and that's what we'll take a look in the
גמרא Gemara it means that you should list explicitly all the names
by which she is also known and therefore there should be no
confusion who you're referring to and everybody should know and the same
by him and the same by the names of the cities. So
therefore list them all in the גט get so that it's very
clear and there's never a confusion about who was the person who
was being divorced and you know who was being divorced. Okay so
now let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר
רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel, said רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, שלחו
ליה בני מדינת הים לרבן גמליאל. Shalchu leih bnei medinas hayam l'Rabban
Gamliel. The people from מדינת הים medinas hayam said to רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, בני אדם הבאים משם לכאן.
Bnei adam habaim misham l'kan. People that are coming from from ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael to here to מדינת הים. medinas hayam. שמו יוסף
וקורין לו יוחנן יוחנן וקורין לו יוסף. Shemo Yosef v'korin lo Yochanan
Yochanan v'korin lo Yosef. So we gotta problem here, okay? That, you
know, where he comes from maybe his original name was יוסף Yosef
but here we call him יוחנן Yochanan or the reverse, you know,
call him יוחנן Yochanan where he originally came from but here in
מדינת הים medinas hayam calling him יוסף. Yosef. It's interesting like those
are two good, you know, good Jewish names, why exactly he changed
it maybe I don't know maybe he wanted to get away from,
you know, from the life he was leaving behind or maybe these
are just substitutes and actually they were using, you know, more secular
names in מדינת הים. medinas hayam. Either way though he says he
goes he's known by different names. Okay. היכי מגרשין נשותיהם? Heichi megarshin
nishoseihem? Now he wants to send a גט get back to his
wife in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Which name should he use? The
name by which he is known here or the name by which
he is known where the גט get is being delivered? And now
this gives a lot more clarity to the משנה'ס Mishnah's concern about
different names and switching the name. So let's take a look. אמר
רבן גמליאל והתקין שיהו כותבין איש פלוני וכל שום שיש לו אשה
פלונית וכל שום שיש לה מפני תיקון עולם. Amar Rabban Gamliel v'hitkin
sheyehu kosvin ish ploni v'chol shum sheyesh lo isha plonis v'chol shum
sheyesh la mipnei tikkun olam. That prompted him to make the תקנה
takkanah that you should write his name and every other name that
they might that he might have in order to deal with any
of that ambiguity. Now again which is the name that you start
with though? Is it the name where in the place where you
are writing or is it the name in the place where it
is being sent and received? You know that is not clear, תוספות
Tosafos has a whole major discussion about that question. Let's see what
the גמרא Gemara says about this. Okay. אמר רב אשי והוא דאיתחזק
בתרי שמי. Amar Rav Ashi v'hu de-itchazak bitrei shemei. That only is
when it's established that he has different names, you know, one name
here and one name over there. Okay.
But
if it's not established that he has another name then you don't
have to do it. Now of course that's a little funny. If
it's not established that he has another name what are you supposed
to do, right? You know so רש"י Rashi says well the the
question would be whether you have to write 'and any other name
that he might have' again in quote marks, right? So again we're
getting to that question whether we're talking about that formulaic 'and any
other name that he might have' or not but if you don't
think that we're talking about a formulaic, right, then what's the point
of ruling well if he's not established two names it's not a
problem, right? I mean obviously we can't write a name we don't
know about. So no so the the relevance of that would be
בדיעבד. b'diavad. Okay. If it was only established of one name and
then later somebody came and said you know after it was written,
well, you know, actually, he's going, he also goes by another name,
then that would not invalidate the גט. get. Okay, so that gets
to an important question about the בדיעבד bedi'eved here also. Was, you
know, in the earlier משנה mishnah as well, we asked the question,
is that, does the תקנה takanah mean בדיעבד bedi'eved it's no good
or not? So here רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel,
right, is it that actually before
רבן גמליאל's תקנה, Rabban Gamliel's takanah, a גט get would be פסול
pasul because it didn't use the right range of names, or was
it a,
or no, if as long as it was a legitimate name in
one of the places where it was written or was received, then
it would be כשר kosher and he was coming and saying that's
not enough though, we need clarity, and if so, what's the הלכה
בדיעבד? halacha bedi'eved? Okay, so if reading this the way רש״י Rashi
does and the emphasis of בדיעבד, bedi'eved, and we'll see what the
גמרא Gemara says in a minute, it's implying that actually sometimes if
you make a mistake, if somebody has to establish names and you,
you know, one here and one there and you only write one,
that it could be פסול בדיעבד. pasul bedi'eved. Either that's the effect
of רבן גמליאל's תקנה, Rabban Gamliel's takanah, or maybe that was true
regardless, maybe his תקנה takanah was trying to prevent that but that's
just a reality that if it's not, if there's that lack of
clarity, then it's not clearly referring to that person and therefore would
be פסול. pasul. So that's a really important question about the status
of the גט בדיעבד. get bedi'eved. Okay, so anyway, but רב אשי
Rav Ashi says if you don't have established two names, then בדיעבד
bedi'eved it is going to be כשר, kosher, and you also don't
have to write a formulaic and any other name that he might
have. אמר ליה רבי אבא לרב אשי, Amar lei Rabbi Abba le-Rav
Ashi, so רבי אבא Rabbi Abba said to רב אשי, Rav Ashi,
רב מרי ורב אלעזר קיימי כוותך, Rav Mari ve-Rav Elazar kaimi kevathach,
you should know that רב מרי Rav Mari and רב אלעזר Rav
Elazar hold like you. תניא כוותיה דרב אשי, Tanya kevathay de-Rav Ashi,
now here we have a ברייתא braita that goes like רב אשי.
Rav Ashi. היו לו שתי נשים, Hayu lo shetei nashim, a man
was married to two wives. אחת ביהודה ואחת בגליל, Achat bi-Yehudah ve-achat
ba-Galil, one in Judea, one in Galilee. ולו שני שמות, Velo shenei
shemot, אחד ביהודה ואחד בגליל, echad bi-Yehudah ve-echad ba-Galil, and he had
two names, one he went by in Judea and one he went
by in Galilee. גירש את אשה שביהודה בשמו שביהודה ואת אשה שבגליל
בשמו שבגליל, Gireish et ishah she-bi-Yehudah bishmo she-bi-Yehudah ve-et ishah she-ba-Galil bishmo
she-ba-Galil, אינה מגורשת. einah megureshet.
Okay,
now here you have the clear בדיעבד bedi'eved ruling. If it was
implicit before, it was explicit here. He went ahead and he did
the normal thing, you know, he divorced a גט get to his
wife in יהודה Yehudah with his Judean name, or his Galilean wife
with his Galilean name, it is not valid, עד שיגרש את אשה
שביהודה בשמו שביהודה ושם דגליל עמו ואת אשה שבגליל בשמו שבגליל ושם
דיהודה עמו. Ad she-yegaresh et ishah she-bi-Yehudah bishmo she-bi-Yehudah veshem de-Galil imo
ve-et ishah she-ba-Galil bishmo she-ba-Galil veshem de-Yehudah imo. Okay,
so you actually have to go ahead and use both names or
else it's בדיעבד פסול. bedi'eved pasul. This is, so there's a lot
of things that's important by this ברייתא. braita. Number one is that
if you don't do this, it is בדיעבד bedi'eved not good. And
again, that raises the question, was that the רבן גמליאל תקנה Rabban
Gamliel's takanah said that I'm going to make it invalid, or was
it, and you know, it gets to the question about how חז״ל
Chazal could be מבטל mevatel a good גט, get, or is it
actually saying something different? Is it saying that because it lacks clarity,
it's דאורייתא פסול de-Oraita pasul גט get and רבן גמליאל's Rabban Gamliel
תקנה takanah was to try to prevent that? But one way or
the other, בדיעבד bedi'eved there are cases בדיעבד bedi'eved where it would
be פסול. pasul. The other thing, בטל batel I should say. The
other thing that emerges from this is that the, it seems that
the default name, you know, the name you begin with, is based
on the place in which it's being
delivered. Okay, so since if he's divorcing his Judean wife and therefore
it's being sent to יהודה, Yehudah, therefore you start with the Judean
name and you add the Galilean name. Okay, so that seems to
be that the name that is started with is based on the
place in which the wife lives and the place in which the
גט get is being received. Okay,
that, and again, תוספות Tosafot has a whole discussion about all of
these things, but that is certainly what emerges from this ברייתא. braita.
בשמו שביהודה ושם דגליל עמו ואת אשה שבגליל בשמו שבגליל ושם דיהודה
עמו,
Bishmo she-bi-Yehudah veshem de-Galil imo ve-et
ishah she-ba-Galil bishmo she-ba-Galil veshem de-Yehudah imo,
when you're divorcing, he was divorcing his wife in the Galilee, he
uses his Galilean name but includes also שם דיהודה עמו shem de-Yehudah
imo and otherwise it actually would be בטל. batel. יצא למקום אחר
וגירש באחד מהם מגורשת. Yatza le-makom acher vegireish be-achad mei-hem megureshet. Now,
if he actually left, you know, went to חוץ לארץ chutz la-aretz
or something and then he, you know, divorced using one of his
names, that would be fine. It's like, huh? What? I don't understand.
He went to חוץ לארץ, chutz la-aretz, but if he's living in
יהודה Yehudah and he uses one of his names or Galilee and
he uses one of his names, it's בטל, batel, but he leaves
and goes to a third place it's going to be okay to
just use one of his names? What sense does that make? So
the גמרא Gemara says, so והא אמרת שם דגליל עמו? ve-ha amart
shem de-Galil imo? Didn't you say that you needed to have both
names? So why is it any different? אלא שמע מינה הא דאתחזק
הא דלא אתחזק שמע מינה. Ela shema mina ha de-itchazek ha de-lo
itchazek shema mina. The difference must be that when he goes to
another place, that other place they don't know that he's got other
names. He goes to, you know, he goes to חוץ לארץ, chutz
la-aretz, he goes to New York, he only is known by his
Judean name. So therefore, you know, in יהודה Yehudah and גליל Galil
they're aware that he's got another name in the other place, and
therefore you have to include it and if not it's בטל. batel.
But if you're in New York and nobody knew that there was
also a Galilean name and he's divorcing his Judean wife, let's assume
he's using his Judean name and divorcing his Judean wife, right, then
in that case it would be כשר kosher and we're not going
to be מבטל mevatel it. Now that makes it sound that the
ביטול bittul is actually a rabbinic ביטול bittul because at the end
of the day, if there is a lack of clarity, just because
we were ignorant and we didn't know he had two names and
we can't be blamed, but if you'd say that objectively speaking, there's
some lack of clarity and that causes a ביטול גט, bittul get,
then that shouldn't matter. Okay, so the fact that we actually are
saying that when you're not to blame and you only knew of
one name that the גט get is going to be כשר kasher
if you didn't have it, but if you do know of the
other name and you don't have it then it's going to be
בטל, botel, that makes it seem very clearly that the ביטול bittul
is something that the חז"ל chazal are being מפקח mepakeach to be
מבטל mevatel the גט, get, which is pretty drastic and something we've
discussed by the previous תיקון עולם tikkun olam as well. Okay, so
now we have that idea that you have to use if you
know of another name it has to be used and if not
it's בטל, botel, that the default name should be or the start
name should be presumably the name of where the גט get is
being delivered, where the wife lives. And but if you're not aware
then what can you do and בדיעבד bedieved the גט get will
be כשר. kasher. Okay.
שמע מינה. shema mina. ההיא דהוה קרו לה מרים ואוקמוצה שרה. hahi
d’hava karu lah Miriam v’ukmusa Sarah. אמר נהרדעי: amar Nahardai: מרים וכל
שום שיש לה ולא שרה וכל שום שיש לה. Miriam vechol shum
sheish lah velo Sarah vechol shum sheish lah. You start the default
name is Miriam because that is the majority and not Sarah. Okay,
now that seems—that's an easy type of a
question because obviously you should default it to the one that's used
more by the majority.
רב משה Rav Moshe deals with interesting questions about let's say somebody
is known by a non-Jewish like a secular name, let's say somebody
was known as Sarah was known as Cynthia or something. So would
you do and Cynthia was the common name, but obviously
some people still knew her as Sarah, so you would start by
Cynthia rather than by Sarah even though it was the non-Jewish name.
That's certainly the גמרא Gemara does not seem to say—that certainly would
seem the פשט pshat of this גמרא Gemara here, doesn't seem to
give preference to secular and non-secular. But the case in the גמרא
Gemara is a pretty simple is a very straightforward one. Obviously you
would go by the one that's majority. The real question that comes
up from the גמרא Gemara two final points about this: one is,
what would be בדיעבד bedieved if you reversed it? Would that really
be a—actually three points: one is, is the גמרא Gemara just saying
that that's the preference? If you reversed it would it then mean,
oh, now it seems like we're talking about some other person because
who knows her as Sarah? Everybody knows her as Miriam. So what
would be the בדיעבד bedieved is not spelled out. The other thing
that's important about this גמרא Gemara is also that here it seems
like we're not talking about a different name in a different place,
we're talking about somebody that goes by multiple names in the same
place. And now we're also introducing that in that case as well
you have to include those additional names, something that was not clear
from before when somebody actually has some nicknames and so on, and
so it's not just a completely different name in a different place.
And the third part is of course the question of whether וכל
שום שיש לה vechol shum sheish lah is formulaic or is it
actually mean list the names? So is the גמרא Gemara saying that
you
write מרים וכל שום שיש לה, Miriam vechol shum sheish lah, you
actually write those words essentially,
or do you actually say Miriam who's also known as Sarah? Again,
that question of whether this is formulaic or not or has to
be filled in remains unclear. Okay, we will end for this for
now.